Hey everybody, welcome back. This is our
last quiz review for the term, quiz three
we'll be talking about, which will be the
last quiz until the final. It's on dynamic
programming, which you guys have been
studying in lectures and recitations and on
your problem sets. Seven and eight, and
lectures 15 through 18, so four lectures.
Quiz one and quiz two material on
essentially data structures and graph
algorithms aren't going to be explicitly
tested, or we're not trying to explicitly
test it, that material on quiz three.
But it is fair game. The material is
cumulative. And so if you have to store
some stuff in a data structure, that's fair
game. But we're not specifically trying to
test you on that material. And really, we
haven't learned all that much new material
in these last four lectures in this last
unit. So this is scope. We're mostly
handling dynamic programming on these four
lectures and recitations and these
two problem sets. But really, the focus is
going to be on this recursive framework
of solving problems with a focus on dynamic
programming specifically. Now, the
recursive framework we have, I think in
previous slides, we used this sort bot
notation. And I think there might be a
space there in previous versions. I'm
concatenating them together here. But
really, it's a framework for solving,
breaking down your problem into a set of
subproblems that can then be related
recursively. And if that relationship
depends on problems in a decreasing or in a
smaller sense, there's a directionality to
which subproblems I'm reducing to
each time I make a recursive call. And that
dependency graph is acyclic.
And so we're trying to find a way to solve
via dynamic programming by memoizing from
bottom up or by calling things and
remembering the calls that we've called
before via memoization. And the basic idea
here is the recursive framework sort bot
that we established is good
for any recursive algorithm.
And once may be used when computing other
subproblems, then we get this really nice
speed up by recognizing that we don't
have to do that work more than once. And
essentially, instead of looking at it as a
tree of recursive calls that may call the
same problems more than once, we look
at it by collapsing those nodes of the same
value down into one. We get a DAG.
And dynamic programming is when those
subproblems overlap. So let's take a look
at our recursive framework here, sort bot.
We have the SRTBOT. I remembered the space
this time. Subproblem, you're going to
define some subproblems. You're going
to relate them recursively. You're going to
specify a topological order of those
subproblems that the relation satisfies.
You're going to list some base cases,
basically wherever you could solve the
subproblem in constant time without doing
any recursive work, stating how you solve
the original problem, which might involve
combining many subproblems but frequently
is just finding one subproblem, and
possibly remembering, storing parent
pointers to return an optimal sequence or
something like that, and then analyze the
time. Now, the last one isn't really
important. It's not really important for
solving a problem recursively. But in this
class, it's really important because we
want to tell whether the algorithms that we
make are efficient. So let's dive a little
deeper into each one of these things. So
when we approach a subproblem, really what
I'm asking you for is to describe,
basically set up a set of subproblems.
Basically, I like to use the variable x,
but you can use whatever variable you want.
You're telling us what's in your memo and
how big your memo is. So we usually have x
as a function of some variables. And you're
wanting to describe to me what the meaning
of that subproblem is in terms of the
parameters. Now, if you have parameters in
your subproblem that don't appear in
your subproblem definition, you're doing it
wrong, and you're probably not going to
get points for the problem, because I don't
know what your subproblem means now. Even
if it's a correct subproblem, and you do
the rest of it right,
part of this class is about communication.
And if you're not communicating to us what
this thing is doing, it's really difficult
for you to convince us that your algorithm
is correct. So you really want to, in
words, describe what the output of your
subproblem is. What will the memo return to
me? And how those return values depend on
the inputs, the parameters of your
subproblem. So that's what, in words,
describe what a subproblem means. So that's
going to be a really important thing for
you not to forget on a quiz. Then when
making subproblems, often what we're doing
is we're recursing on different values of
indices in a sequence or numbers in your
problem. That's kind of what we got to in
the last, in lecture 18, I guess, when we
were talking about expanding subproblems
based on an integer. In our problem now,
actually, an integer in our problem is
the number of things in a sequence. And so
really, those indices are integers in our
problem that we're looping over, except
those integers happen to be the size of our
subproblem, whereas other integers might
be larger, which is why you might get
a pseudo polynomial time bound. But in
general, when I have a sequence of things
that I might want to dynamic program over,
common choices for subproblems are prefixes
or suffixes if I can kind of locally
figure out what to do with one item
and then recurse. Or if I can't kind of
localize it by one choice on one side, if I
have to make a choice in the middle or I
have to make a choice on both ends, then
you might want to use basically contiguous
subsequences of your sequence, because you
might need that flexibility when recursing
downward if you need to take something from
both the front and the back, for example.
And really, what's the difference between
prefixes and suffixes? Not much. We've been
concentrating on suffixes in this class
because in some sense, it's easier to think
about. What am I doing with the first thing
in my sequence or my suffix? And then I
could recurse on what happens later. Now,
in actuality, when you're doing this, say,
bottom up, the actual computation that is
evaluated first is where in that sequence?
I may be calling at the top level what
happens to my first element, but I'll
actually deal with that first element
last, because I will recursively solve
everything below me, in front of me, before
I figure out what to do with this thing.
So in actuality, when I'm solving
my recursion, I will start at the end and
bottom up, because that's my base case. And
then I'll work my way back to the front.
Whereas with prefixes, you look at it the
other way. What do I'm doing with my last
element? If I look at what I'm doing with
the last element, I recurse on a prefix on
the stuff that's before me. And then when
I do bottom up, I start from the front and
work my way up. It's two different sides
of the same coin. And usually, these are
interchangeable. We've been doing it suffix
-wise, because when we're starting to
learn dynamic programming, we read things
from left to right and things like that.
It's a lot easier to figure out what's
happening with the first thing and move
forward conceptually. It's actually exactly
the same thing. I could just flip my
sequence, do the exact same thing
with prefixes. It would be the exact same
dynamic program. So these things
are interchangeable. It's just it's really
useful when learning into dynamic program
to be able to switch back and forth between
these things. We'll be working on suffixes
today on the problems that we do. But these
are interchangeable. And sometimes it's
useful to be able to conceptually think
about it in both directions.
So aside from dealing with subsequences of
sequences, in particular contiguous ones,
we often multiply our subsets across
multiple inputs, like if we have multiple
sequences, we might take indices in
each one of them to represent prefixes or
suffixes. And then we might have to
remember additional information by
maintaining some auxiliary information,
like am I trying to maximize or minimize my
sum in an evaluated expression in
an arithmetic parenthesization? Or is it
player one's turn or player's two turn?
Or where was my finger when I was playing
piano or something like that? Those are the
kinds of things that we might expand our
state on. And in particular, we might
expand our state based on the numbers in
our problem if we're trying to, for
example, keep track of how much space is
left in a knapsack or something like that.
But in general, if I'm trying to, say, pack
a set of things, it's useful to know how
much space I have left to pack. So that's
subproblems. This is really the key part
about dynamic programming, is the recursive
part. This is what makes it hard, is
choosing a set of subproblems. And it's
often you build subproblems to fit well
with a relation. So usually, building what
these subproblems are is usually closely
coupled with the next step, which is
relating the subproblems recursively.
And by relate recursively, I usually what I
want is an expression, a mathematical
expression relating the definition of a
subproblem you had in the previous section,
relating those in math terms to the other
things. It's really important that you
write this in math because it needs to be
precise to communicate this thing well.
Now, you can write it in words. But I would
suggest you write it as a mathematical
expression because it's a lot more concise
for us to see what's happening in
your recursion. So relate them recursively.
Basically, I'm going to write, say, that x
of some set of parameters equals some
function, usually a maximization or a
minimization or a summation or an or or an
and or some other combinator of a bunch of
choices that you might make or a bunch of
subproblems that you might recurse on. So
basically, you're going to depend on some
other subproblems that are smaller in some
sense. Now, actually embedded in this, the
idea of a smaller subproblem isn't really
well -defined yet. We haven't told you an
ordering of these subproblems to be
smaller. But that's what's going to come in
the third step. So kind of a strategy for
figuring out what these recursive relations
might be is to identify some question about
the subproblem solution. What do I do with
the first character
in this string?
Or which cage do I put this tiger in to
figure out what subproblem should I recurse
on later? I don't know the answer to that
question. But if I knew the answer to that
question, then I could recurse on a smaller
subproblem because I've figured out what
to do with that tiger. And so it will let
me reduce to smaller subproblems. And then
what dynamic programming does is
because I only have a polynomial number of
subproblems and I've assumed I've already
computed what those are, I've already
memorized what the solutions to those
subproblems are, then I can just locally
brute force over all the possible answers
to that question. And that's just one way
to look at dynamic programming.
So then as we were talking about
topological order, arguing that relation is
acyclic, essentially just defining what
smaller means when we say we're recursing
on smaller subproblems. What does smaller
mean? Usually, you're saying that some
index or some parameter of my subproblem
always decreases or increases. Sometimes
that's not always the case. Sometimes you
have to maybe add a couple indices and see
that that always increases because one may
stay the same while the other increases or
something like that. But in general, as
long as you argue that the relations are
acyclic, then the subproblem graph is a DAG
and you can compute in a bottom -up manner
and you don't get infinite
loops in your recursion.
The last couple of things are bookkeeping.
But if you don't write these on your exam,
we can't give you points for them. So write
these down. Base cases, if you don't tell
us base cases, then your algorithm cannot
be polynomial time. It can't even be finite
time because your algorithm never stops. It
just continues to recurse forever and ever
and ever. And so it's hard to give us
points. I mean, we will give you some
points if your subproblems and relation
are correct. But really, if you write code
without a base case, it's going to be
wrong. So base cases are really important.
Basically, for anything at the bounds of
your computation, wherever your recursive
relation would essentially go outside the
bounds of your memo, let's say I'm dealing
with a subsequence. And at some point,
I'm trying to point to a state where I have
zero or negative elements in my sequence.
That's probably a bad thing. And so I want
to define how to compute those things
in constant time so that my algorithm can
terminate when it gets to one of those base
cases. So it's really important that you
cover all of those possible leaf locations
where you want to be able to return in
constant time. And we'll do some of that
today. State solutions for all reachable
independent subproblems where the relation
breaks down. Essentially, I would be going
outside the bounds of my thing or anything
where maybe if you've got one item left,
you might say, well, I have no choice on
what to do with that item. I have to pick
it or something like that. OK, then for
your original problem, you show how to
compute solution to the original problem
from the solutions of your subproblems. So
usually, this is just, here's a subproblem.
It's the one that used all of the things.
And that's going to be my answer. But
that's not always the case. Sometimes, like
in a longest increasing subsequence, we had
to take a max over all of our subproblems
that we computed or max
subarray sum. We also had to do that.
But in general, the output to our
subproblems wants to be some scalar value
that we're trying to optimize or a
Boolean or something like that. It's how we
maximize or minimize what we're doing.
We're not storing the entire sequence of
how we got there because there could be an
exponential number of possible subsequences
that got there. That's the whole point
of dynamic programming. We're kind of
isolating the complexity of one
subproblem down to a single number.
But in a lot of problems, we might want to
reconstruct, say, the placement of tigers
into cages and not just what's the minimum
discomfort over all tigers or something
like that, like you add in your problem
set. So I actually want to know where to
put tigers into cages. And to do that,
every time I maximize a subproblem, I can
remember which subproblem or subproblems
I depended on, just like storing parent
pointers in shortest paths. And then using
those parent pointers, I can just walk back
in my subproblem graph and figure out which
path to a base case led me to an optimal
solution.
And then the last thing is analyzing
running time. Generally, you're just
summing the work done by each
subproblem because the assumption is you're
calculating all of the subproblems
you described to me. But if the work per
subproblem is bounded by the same value,
you can just multiply it out. So that's
generally a weaker bound, but usually
asymptotically equivalent. To the stronger
notion on the left.
And that's basically how you do running
time. Usually, it's enough to, how do I
define, determine how many subproblems
I have? Well, I look at the possible values
of each of my parameters. And then I
multiply those numbers together. A lot of
people will maybe say, oh, I add them
together. No, because I'm able to choose
each of these independently. And so I
multiply those things together. And then
the work done by each subproblem is usually
the size of the thing I'm maximizing over
or minimizing over or summing in
my relation. It's going to be the size of
that, the branching that I have, the number
of subproblems I depend on. And so the
number of subproblems, you probably look
at your subproblem statement definition. To
find the work done by each subproblem,
you look at your recursive relation.
So with that, we've got this really nice
framework. And we're going to use it to
solve some practice problems. Happy days.
And these are a little bit longer in terms
of
description than our previous quiz to
review. So I'm going to go ahead and read
them out for you. This one's a little
shorter. Tiffany Bannon stumbles upon a
lottery chart dropped by a time traveler
from the future, winning lottery numbers
and positive integer cast payouts for the
next n days. Anyone get the reference here?
Tiffany Bannon.
Biff Tannen from some Back to the Future
thing. So this was actually, I think it's
the second Back to the Future movie where
this happens. Anyway, Tiffany wants to use
this information to make money because she
knows the future about the lottery, but is
worried that if she plays winning
numbers every day, the organizers will get
suspicious and shut her down. So the idea
here is maybe it's still suspicious, but
decides to play the lottery infrequently,
at most twice in any seven -day period. She
will. She'll win. But it's infrequent
enough that maybe that's by chance, maybe
not. Describe a linear time algorithm to
determine the maximum amount of lottery
winnings Tiffany can win in the next n days
by playing the lottery infrequently. Now,
this was a particularly difficult type of
PSET, or first PSET on dynamic programming
problem, but let's try to do it together.
So this is problem one. I'm going to just
call it Lotto.
OK, so how can we deal with subproblems
here? Well, I might want to think about
what do I do on the first day? Am I going
to play the lottery or not? Curse on the
rest. That sounds good, right? So I might
have something like, well, let's say that L
of i is the
winnings on day i. This is kind of just
like, this doesn't define me some notation
on what the cash payouts are, and so I'm
making a variable to do that. And for the
sake of what's written down on my sheet,
I'm going to assume that this is 1 indexed.
I don't know why. OK, so I have days 1 to
n. I know what their lottery payouts are.
So I might, when I'm doing my sort bot
stuff, I have subproblems, right? What I
might want to do is see what happens on day
1 and recurse on what's later. So I might
have something like x of i is max winnings
for, I guess, possible for days i to n.
Anyone have a problem with this type
of subproblem? Let's see. Let's kind of see
what this type of
subproblem would lead me to.
I can either, in my reload step, what are
my choices? I can either play on day i or I
can not play on day i. If I,
I'm trying to maximize this thing.
Maximize. Either if I play on day i, I get
L i, and then I can recurse on the
remainder. Or I don't play on L i, and I
recurse on the remainder.
Or I make careful mistake adherence,
right? I can always pick perhaps.
It's within any consecutive seven day
period, which is a little confusing. How
can I remember what days I'm allowed to
pick later on? It seems a little daunting.
OK. In a sense, for me to know, like this
is max winning possible for days i to n.
But in some sense, it depends on which
days I picked before. Right. Because if I
picked i minus 1, I can't pick another day
for another six days. If I have a right.
So I have let's do this precisely. This is
i minus 1. Right. I have seven day period
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7. Right. If I played
the lottery here, and I played the lottery
here, then I'm not allowed to play the
lottery here. I'm not allowed to play here,
not allowed to play here, not allowed to
play here. I'm not allowed to play here, I
am allowed to play.
Here so this is i plus 1 plus 2
plus 3 plus 4 plus 5 plus 6 i plus 6.
So depending on what happened before me, I
might not be able to play until day i plus
6. But if I haven't played until since
way back here, I could potentially play the
next guy. I don't actually know which of
these I can play on next. In some sense, I
need to remember which days I'm allowed
to play on next. And I want to be able to
just, like at the beginning, I have no
restrictions. I can just play on this guy
next, even if I played there.
But in general, I will be restricted in
some way between being able to play on this
guy and being able to play on this guy.
And so what I'm going to do is I'm going to
generalize my subproblems by storing
additional information so that I can rely
on that information when I
look into the future and recurse.
So instead of I'm going to, in some
sense, need to remember two days.
Where was the last two places I played?
I'm going to simplify that a little bit by
saying that this subproblem, max winnings
possible for days i to n, I'm going to say
that I have to play on day i.
and so on.
OK, so I'm going to expand this
problem by another, I guess this is a j.
OK, assuming I play on day i and
I'm allowed to play, I guess, and next
allowable
play on day i plus j for,
what are my possible
range of days for j?
I can either play the next day, but I never
restricted past day i plus 6, because the
things before me further to the right,
because I haven't dealt with them yet. So I
only have to deal with this from 1 to 6.
Well, this is nice, because it expanded my
subproblems by a constant number.
So I actually didn't lose anything
asymptotically here by remembering this
information. But I'm able to remember all
the things that could have happened before
me. I compress it into this one number.
So now let's rewrite our relation. I'm
actually going to go ahead and use some
more board space, because I
think that's easier than erasing.
So we are looking at my relation. This is
a pretty complicated relation, but what's
happening now? Now, I'm assuming I play
on day i. That actually simplifies things a
little bit, because no matter what, I get
the winnings on day i. Now, when I call
this subproblem, I better make sure that
it's OK that I played on day i, but that's
for my caller. I am locally allowed to play
on day i. I am playing on day i. That's
the definition of my subproblem.
So I'm going to maximize
over some choice,
max of,
I guess I have li no matter what. So this
could actually come out of my max. And then
I'm going to choose, what am I choosing
here? I'm not choosing whether I'm playing
on day i. I'm choosing what my next day I
play is, so that then I can recurse on that
subproblem.
Play on. Well, I'm restricted
by this j parameter that I
didn't add into my subproblem
on what possible days I can play next. I'm
going to split that into a kind of compress
that into one thing. So x, I can play on. I
have a choice of the next day I play. I'm
going to compare between j, which is my
next allowable play, and sometime in the
future.
So i plus k, this is going to be my loop
that I'm looping over in terms of my max.
And then what am I restricted on in my
play? It depends on how far I am from i. So
if I'm here,
i, if I choose k to be the next day, I
can't play for many, many times. So the
subproblem I'm going to recurse on is,
this is i plus k. I'm going to recurse on i
plus k. But I'm not able to, j needs to
be the max it can be, because I can't play
until i plus 6. So this i plus k plus 6 is
going to be my thing. So let's see. So I'm
going to put,
let's see if I can unpack what I wrote
down here. Max of 1, 7 minus k. Yuck.
Oh, I'll put it here. 1,
7 minus k. OK, if I pick k,
I'm not aggressive toward these boards.
It's justness. OK, so if I get, if I pick a
k way down here, right, I'm not restricted
at all, right? And so the most permissive
option I have here is 1. So I definitely
can't be worse than 1. But if I pick,
and then this needs to be some number
between 6 and 1. And so I can just check
the other bound. If this is the most
restrictive, then this should be 6. So when
k equals 1, this should be 6. And it
decreases every time further back or
further forward I choose this k, right? So
that's what my subproblem is going to be.
And I'm choosing over k in from j, j,
sorry, i plus j. Sorry, j. Thank you. Until
what?
That's the question. Until what? Do I have
to loop over n? If I loop over n, I'm going
to get a quadratic running time, which
is worse than what I'm allowed to do. The
assumption is that I only have to check a
constant number of these. And why might
that be?
Any ideas? Let's say I got my subproblem.
I'm recursing. I've got i. Yeah, I don't
know where j is. j is somewhere over here.
1, 2, 3, maybe it's 4 or something like
that.
Let's say I pick some k down here. What is
this? This is i plus, so this is j is 4, 5,
6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15. 15,
way over here, like two weeks later. Is it
ever optimal for me to do that? Why not?
You could play the lotto in the middle.
Yeah, I could play the lotto in the middle.
Here, right? Right. I'm within, like, from
here to there, that's a seven -day period
where I only played once. And from here to
here, that's a seven -day period where I
only played once. Right? So it's going to
be more, these are positive values, so it's
going to be more optimal for me to choose
something in here to play. Right? So how
far, I mean, I could just use 15, and that
would satisfy. Right? Because I've already
argued to you that it's never optimal to, I
can check this. It's not going to be
optimal. It's going to be more optimal to
play sometime over here. Right?
But how far do I have to check?
Well, maybe I have to check
up to seven. Does that work?
Not quite. So let's say I played here and I
played here and I played here and I played
here. Right? I actually, can't play here,
here, here, here, here. Right? I'm not
allowed to play those. I guess
these should be O's. I played there.
And I'm not allowed to play here. One, two,
three, four, five. Right? But I am allowed
to play anywhere in here. So I basically
want to shrink this until these x's
collide with each other, because then it's
possible that an optimal solution would
require me to pick these two and then
require me to pick these two way over
there. Right? So this is 10 things in the
middle. I only have to go up to at most 11.
OK? That's 11. Now, you could use any
constant above 11 and get the same running
time bound, but that's my analysis. OK. So
we have our recursive relation. And so what
am I doing? I'm just looping over my
choices of next day to play. I'm recursing
on this thing where I actually do play on
that day. Right? But I'm remembering the
information about what I'm allowed to play
next by limiting based on what my previous
value was. OK? So that's the kind of key
thing. I'm remembering something further in
advance. Or I'm remembering what
happened in the past by describing it as a
restriction of something in the future. OK?
So this was a pretty difficult problem. I
think it was one of our first dynamic
programming problems on that term. It was
probably a little ambitious. OK. Well,
you're saying this recurrence goes up to
11. Hm. JASON KUO - Yes. The recurrence
goes up to 11. Not 10. 11. OK. So we have
our topological sort. What's a topological
sort for these subproblems? Anybody?
JASON KUO - k is always going to be a
positive number, right? Because j goes from
1 to 6. So I'm always going to be
increasing in this first quantity. Right?
So for x of i, j, i always,
or sorry, depends
on strictly
on the larger i. Right? So this i,
when I call subproblems, it always calls
subproblems with a larger i. Now, this is a
little weird because I wanted me to depend
on smaller subproblems.
Smaller. Now, it is smaller because
I'm taking a smaller suffix. But it's
corresponding to using a larger number. To
me, that's a little confusing. But that's
OK because we're kind of using things
that are always monotonically going in some
direction. So this is corresponding to a
smaller subproblem in some measure. Right?
It's the number of elements that we're
actually recursing on. In some sense, if we
wrote this as a prefix, we would have us
depending on strictly smaller i. And that
would be more natural in terms of a
recursing on smaller subproblems. But I
digress. OK? All right. Then we have our
original subproblem. I'm going to, I can't
move this board. I'll just keep going
because we have lots of boards. OK? Our
original subproblem. Now,
what could I do? I
have to start somewhere.
Right? Here, my subproblems assume that
I'm starting at i. But I don't know where I
start. I could start by taking the first
element. But I might not. So I could just
take the max over all i
of xi. What?
The first one, I'm not restricted on what I
choose next. So what's the most permissive
version of j? 1. Right? I'm allowed to take
the next day. Right? So if I just take the
max over all of these subproblems, I'll
get the solution. Now, actually, this is a
little bit more work than I need. This is
looping over all n. Right? It's definitely
correct. Right? Because I have to start
somewhere. But will I ever start after the
first, I don't know, 7? No. Right? So I
could just take this max over the first
some constant number. And that would be
fine. But that's OK. This is still smaller
than the number of subproblems that we
have. Yeah? If I were being lazy during my
exam and I looped over j, would that be
correct? JASON KURIYAMA - If I looped over
j for? I took the max over every possible
thing? JASON KURIYAMA - Took the loop over
this and j? Yeah. JASON KURIYAMA - Yeah.
That would still be fine. Why not? It's
just less. It's more restrictive of
subproblems. It will never be better to do
that. But you could do that because it
wouldn't change your running time. JASON
KURIYAMA - Could it change my running time
if my j accidentally looped too far? JASON
KURIYAMA - Well, j is restricted to be 1 to
6. So I don't think so. But in a different
problem in a different context, it could.
OK. So that's the original. And then time
here.
What do we got? We have a linear number of
subproblems, number of subproblems. We've
got,
I actually like usually saying exactly how
many subproblems I have. Oh, we didn't do
base case. I missed
bot. I missed my b. We'll
do the original first and then the base
case. OK. Base case. What do we have as our
base case here? Well, when
I don't have anything to do.
And actually, if I have this situation
for i equals, say, n, I got my last thing,
I could potentially start looping over
subproblems that are negative in terms of
my index. I'm not going to want to do that.
There's a couple of ways I can deal with
that.
If I have my subproblems for negative
i, that's one thing I could do. But then I
have to remember, or I have to figure out
how far I go into the negative. That's one
thing I could do. And I give a base
case for each of those cases. I don't have
anything. So I get
like a, I don't know,
zero value for playing in the future.
Because I have negative things. I can't do
anything with that. Another way of handling
that, which I think I did in my solutions,
was restrict that k
to only be, I guess, and restrict that i
plus k is less than or equal to n. And then
I'll never go to negative subproblems. I'll
never recurse on these things. But that
means that when I call this on n,
when I only have one lottery day left,
n is negative
negative對対, then the
answer's dominant total,
but你的maix? case, xij, I guess we could put
this at n equals 0, or sorry, equals L of
i,
L of n. Thank you. Because
at the last guy, I have to use ln.
So there it is. Now, in actuality, if you
write this correctly, I put the L i outside
and I union this with a 0, I can actually
get away with just having the relation and
no base case, because my relation actually
reduces to a base case because of the way
that I wrote my relation. But in general,
you'll want to write some kind of base case
here to either acknowledge that your
relation handles it, or be specific about
what happens when I can't do any more work.
All right, so and the last thing, time,
we've got n subproblems exactly times
constant work per subproblem, because I'm
looping over 11 possible values. Actually,
it's up to 11, because j could be 6.
So this is order n work total. So this is
a pretty daunting first problem. But in
terms of what Professor Domain was
talking about last lecture in terms of
categorization of subproblem, or
categorization of dynamic programs, what do
we got? We've got a suffix subproblem,
where we expanded by some local
information, remembering when the
next time I can play. So that's kind of a
categorization of these subproblems. The
recurrence relation has constant branching,
but more than two branching.
And I'm combining a bunch of subproblems in
my original evaluation. And if I wanted to
figure out what days Tiff should play on
the lottery, you can store parent pointers
when I'm evaluating this max. I figure out
which subproblem x I recursed that gave me
the max. And I can walk back to see which
choices I made to figure out which days I
played the lottery.
Does that make sense?
So any questions on problem one? That's the
most, I want to have the most complicated
one first, so that we could have an easier
way to go. In a sense, this is the most
complicated version of this kind of
actually pretty simple dynamic programming
setup. Why do I say simple dynamic
programming setup? It's just suffixes. And
I'm just doing a constant amount of work
local to me. It's just a very complicated
local setup. But that's what I mean by
simple. When we're designing subproblems,
this is one that we could, I mean, when
we're designing problems for this dynamic
programming setup, it's one of the hardest
from a, it's one of the easiest from a
conceptual standpoint, but one of the
hardest to actually implement. Okay. So
problem two, this
one's a longing.
Okay. A wealthy family, Alice, Bob,
and their young son, Charlie, are sailing
around the world. When they encounter a
massive storm, Charlie is thrown overboard,
presumed drowned. Okay. This is very
colorful language for these problems that
are in the writers. 20 years later, a man
comes to Alice and Bob claiming to be
Charlie, having maybe been marooned on an
island for that long. Okay. Alice and Bob
are excited but skeptical, and they order a
DNA matching test from the genetic testing
company, 46 and V. Given Alice and Bob,
sorry, given three length N DNA sequences,
basically strings of CGTA or something like
that, from each of Alice's and Bob's DNA,
Alice, Bob, and Charlie, the testing center
will determine three, their ancestry as
follows. If Charlie's DNA can be
partitioned into two, not necessarily
contiguous, subsequences of equal length,
so basically I take, I can take the, if I
have N is length five, or length six, it's
better to be even. I need to find three
characters in order, and then
the other three characters,
must match to make some substrings in, some
subsequences in Alice and Bob's DNA. Okay.
So there's, that's a little hard to parse,
so let's look at an example here. For
example, Alice's DNA is AATT. Bob's DNA is
CCGG. If Charlie's DNA were CATG, they'd be
matched, right? Because CG is a subsequence
of Charlie's DNA, and is a subsequence of
Bob's DNA. And AT is a subsequence of
Charlie's DNA, and is also a subsequence of
Alice's DNA. And so we've partitioned them
into two equal length subsequences. These
are not necessarily consecutive
subsequences, but just any subsequences,
such that,
that they appear in Alice and Bob. But if
Charlie would be found to be an imposter,
if his DNA sequence were AGTC,
essentially it's easy to realize that,
because G and C are swapped, in terms of
their ordering, and GC, the letters GC only
appear in Bob's DNA, and don't appear in
that order. Right? So it's easy to see that
he's an imposter with these strings, but
you can imagine with longer strings, this
could be difficult to solve. Right? So we
want an n to the fourth time algorithm, to
determine whether Charlie is a fraud. Okay.
So, I actually shortened this last night.
This is like twice as long on the problem
set, so, yeah, anyway. So how do
we approach this problem? Yes?
No, they don't have to be contiguous, like
in the example. It would be matched if C
and G is a subsequence, not contiguous,
of C, A, T, G. Yeah? So that's an important
part of this problem. I'm just, I'm not
trying to figure out if there's, basically
there are only two sub, contiguous
subsequences of length 2n, that this thing
can be partitioned in. I just look in the
middle. No. We're looking for subsequences,
not substrings. So, they kind of interleave
like this in some way, and there's
actually a number of different ways I
can partition that. There's actually an
exponential number of ways. So, that's
a problem, potentially. Yes? Is there a
biological basis? No, there's no biological
basis to this thing that I know of. Okay.
All right. So, how do we solve this
problem? What problem does this look like?
I mean, it seems like string matching.
Right? So, I might want to think it's
something like longest common subsequence.
Right? But here I have three sequences
instead of two sequences. And we've got
this other weird condition where we kind of
need an exact partition of Charlie.
Right? I need to use all of the letters in
Charlie, but I don't have to use all of the
letters in Alice and Bob. Right? So, let's
just, let's get some notation here. You
know, A, B, and C are n length strings.
Right?
So, what could I do? Let's
define some subproblems. If I were
to go via longest common subsequence, I
might keep track of an index of a suffix or
prefix of each one of these strings. Right?
That kind of makes sense. Something like
I, J, K, where we're
talking about the suffixes,
sorry, that's prefixes, I, B, J, and C, K.
Right? That seems reasonable, at least.
Right? It's what we would do
for longest common subsequence.
What's the problem here?
I mean, I could match this guy with one of
these guys or decide to skip it and match
one of these guys and decide to
skip it. But if I do that, I might get
a subsequence.
But actually, I always need to match all
of C. So, that might make sense. I always
need to match all of C.
Right? So, in a sense,
let's see. Let's see.
How can I do this?
I need to match all of C, but I also need
to make sure I'm using exactly n over 2
characters from C in Boo. I'm exactly n
over 2 characters from C in A. Does that
make sense? So, how can I satisfy that
condition? Now I understand why I used
prefixes before. And I
swapped it to suffixes here.
But we'll make it work.
How can I remember how many characters
I assigned from Alice versus Bob? Right? As
I'm matching characters
in Alice and Bob,
I need to kind of remember where they
point to or how many I've already used in
Charlie so that I can
divvy up the remainder
in here. Oh, actually, this works in a
different sense. There's like 18 different
ways we could do this. So, OK. So, I need
to remember how many I've already used up
so that I can be sure to allocate exactly
that many characters in the future to
either Alice or Bob. Right?
So, how can I remember that?
I can just remember
how many do I...
I'll do it the way that I did it before,
which is I can remember two different
things here. I can remember how many things
I have left to match in Alice in C, or I
can remember how many things I've already
matched in C to Alice. OK? If I talk about
how many things I've already matched, then
I can index this thing by the sum of those
things. If I talk about how many things
I have yet to match, I have to do like n
minus the things. OK? So, those are the
different parameters that we can do. We'll
do what's in my notes,
and I'll try to fix it.
OK.
So, what we're going to do is remember
or figure out how many things I'm still
needing to match in C to Alice and
Bob. Right? So, I'm going to call this K...
Sorry. KI. I is associated with A, and B
is associated with J. And KJ. OK? This is
going to be the...
I have to write this down. Well, OK. So,
this is going to be... What kind of output
do I want to my subproblem? I just want to
know if these things are... If he's a fraud
or not. So, this is going to
be a Boolean. Right? So, true if
can match
KI length.
Subsequence of suffix
A suffix is this guy.
And length KJ. I guess KJ length.
Subsequence of suffix BJI. Or BJ suffix.
Right?
To all characters in... And now, what is
this in? This is the hard part. Do I need a
separate index for C?
To know where I am in C?
In a sense, yes. I need to know where I am
in C. How much I have to match. Right? But
if I need to match KI to KJ to all of them,
then there better be KI plus J things left
in C. Right? So, in a sense, I don't need
to remember that information again. It's
not independent to my other parameters.
I can compute it. Right? I can throw it in,
but I can determine it from the other
parameters. Right? So, I want to match it
with the suffix of C. Of length KI plus KJ.
So, I think this is the only part that is
going to be annoying to me.
Okay. So, this should be suffix
of all of the things
minus KI minus KJ minus 1.
It's just this. And why is that? Okay. If
I've matched everything, KI and KJ are both
0. And I should have nothing in C,
which should be N colon. Okay? We're zero
indexed. Yes, we are. Whenever I use Python
notation, I better be zero indexed. Okay.
Does this make sense as a subproblem?
I mean, it's confusing. Hopefully, it makes
sense. Right? What I'm going to try to
do is I'm going to match some number of
characters in this suffix, which is
hopefully longer than KI. Right? Otherwise,
I'm going to be in a base case where this
is impossible. Right? And some subsequence
of this matched completely
into this. All right. So, those
are my subproblems. I'm
going to try to relate them now.
XIJ, KI, KJ. What is this going to equal?
All right. Well, we've got Booleans. So,
this is AND false otherwise. Okay. That's
a Boolean. All right. So, I just need some
subproblem I recurse on to be true. So,
what's the combinator for some of a bunch
of choices, Boolean choices, any one of
which may be true? I want to combine a
bunch of them. I just want to see if any of
them are true. I'm going to OR over them.
Okay? And I'm going to OR over four
choices. Okay? What are my choices? Either
the first thing in A matches with C. The
first thing in B matches with C. Or I don't
match with either. Right? So, those are my
four choices. So, if I match with A, I plus
1, I recurse on a
smaller suffix of A. And A
by adding, oh, this all just
works. Great. KJ, this is I.
If AI equals CI and AI is greater than 0.
Right? So, if KI is greater than 0, I need
to match an I. Right? So, this conditional
doesn't even make sense unless I've
evaluated this KI to be bigger than 0.
Otherwise, I'm trying to access I of N.
Right? So, I'm just putting this
conditional on there. Same with matching B.
I, J plus 1, KI, KJ plus 1. If, sorry, this
should be minus 1. I have fewer characters
that I have to recurse on.
So, that's a typo in my notes.
So, C, oh, this is not CI. What is this?
It's whatever that thing is. So, I'm going
to just say question mark.
And KJ is greater than 0. So, I'll fill
that in in the notes. It's going to be some
complicated expression that looks like
that. Okay. It's exactly that expression.
Yes. That it is.
So, it's that thing.
Assuming if I less than N. Right? I don't
want to move off the end of this thing. Or
XI, J plus 1, KI, KJ. If J is less than N.
Okay. So, those are my four choices. If I
matched a letter, I'm great. Otherwise, I
decrease the size of my subproblem. And I
recurse.
Okay?
So, fun recursion. Topological sort. Right?
These subproblems only depend on what?
Larger I? Not quite.
Larger J? Not quite.
Changing K or J. These don't even change
here. So, we're going to use depend on
larger. I guess strictly. That's kind of an
important thing. I plus J. Right? Because
at least one of these two things is
increasing. And then the nice thing about
that is it kind of tells us when we should
stop. Right? We should stop when either I
or J get to N. We should know enough
at that point to be able to determine if we
succeeded or not. Possibly.
So, we have our base case.
What's the easy base case? When we
succeeded. When have we succeeded?
If we have nothing left in A and B. And
we have nothing left in C. Right? I have
nothing left to match. So, I have N. N.
And I don't need to match anything else.
That's just going to be true. Right? All
roads point to this subproblem to get to a
true solution. Right? Otherwise, we
have some false base cases. If you set us
something up like this, and you only give
us a base case that's true, and you're or
-ing over the things, your answer will
always be true. So, you're not having any
discriminatory power. At all. If you give
us a true base case, you better be giving
us some false base cases. Or one, at least.
So, in the case where the first one is N,
and we have some I, K, J,
this is going to
be false if what?
If we have nothing left in A, I, or O,
but this guy is positive, we got problems.
Right? Otherwise, this thing is 0. And
we'll just try to match everything up here.
And eventually, we'll get down to this base
case or something where this thing goes to
0, and we got a problem.
And the same goes for the other
side as well. If we run out of things in B,
when the number of things we need to match
in B is greater than 0. OK? So, those are
our base cases.
The original problem is what?
Yeah. It's just going to be one of our
subproblems, N, N, and then N over 2, and N
over 2. Right? I'm trying to match half
of the things in C with half of the things.
Right?
0. Thank you.
Because we're 0 index. Yes. Again, that's
switching from prefix to suffix in the
middle is fun. So, anyway. And it better
be the case that N is 2, or else it's
obviously false. Or is even, or
else this is obviously false. OK?
And then the last thing, which I'm not
going to write down, is we have a constant
work here. Right? Because I'm just checking
the value of four subproblems and a
conditional for each. And I have how many
subproblems? I loops over N, J loops over
N, K and KJ loop over N over 2. So, I get
a quartic number of subproblems, quartic
running time as desired. OK? So, I'm not
going to write that down. It was quite a
bit late.
Let's do one more problem, which is sad,
because the last one's about Gokiman Po,
which is a fun, fun problem. Gokiman Po
basically relies on, I'm trying to catch a
bunch of pocket monsters. Just monsters, I
think, is in this. And you can either go to
a location and catch
that monster for free.
But that costs money, because I have to
ride share there. OK? Or I don't have to go
to that location, and I buy it on my
in -app purchase. But that costs me a
different amount of money. OK? But buying
it in -app purchase kept me at the location
I was previously, wherever I was. And
so, the point of that problem is I need to
remember where I was last, so that I know
how far I need to travel to get to my next
monster. OK. So, that's, going to be the
last one that I'm not going to be able to
get to. Number three
is a problem about tapas. OK. So, these
all come from spring 18. The first two came
from a problem set. These next two come
from the final exam that year. OK. Albert
Ratkins,
he's on a diet. But he has a dinner at an
upscale tapas bar, where he got many, he's
going to order many small plates. OK? There
are n plates of food on the menu, where
each plate has a certain information. It
has a volume, a number of calories in that
dish, and a sweetness label. Basically,
0 or 1, whether it's sweet or not. OK?
But he's on a diet, and he wants to eat no
more than k calories during his meal, but
wants to fill his stomach as much as
possible, because he wants to feel full.
Right? So, he wants to maximize the volume
that he fills, even though he wants to
reduce the number of calories, or restrict
the number of calories. OK? He also wants
to order exactly s sweet plates. OK?
So, we've got this other condition, where I
need to make sure I'm eating a certain
number of sweet plates. It might be useful
for me to remember how many sweet plates
I've already eaten, so I make sure that I
eat that number. OK? Without purchasing
the same dish twice. OK. So, here's a
condition that's similar to the knapsack
0, 1 problem versus a knapsack kind of
general problem. Am I allowed to take more
than one of these things or not? Here, it's
a restriction that I'm not allowed to take
a plate more than once. OK? And I'm going
to try to describe an order nks time
algorithm to find the maximum volume of
food Obert can eat, given his diet. OK. So,
first thing I'm going to note here is one
of the things that we talked about at the
last dynamic programming lecture was, is
this a polynomial running time that it's
asking me for? Right? Actually, on your
problem set 8, you were asked on each
problem to categorize whether the running
time of your algorithm was polynomial or
not. And actually, you don't have to solve
the problem in order to answer that
question if we give you the running time.
Right? If we give you the running time, you
can just take a look at that running time
and be like, oh, is that polynomial in the
size of my input? And here it is, is it?
All the ones previously were. This one was
in order n. That was in order n squared,
because n was the number of things in my
input, the number of words it took to give
you that input. Here, what do I have? I
have a triple of numbers for each plate.
There are n of them. So, n is polynomial.
S is polynomial. Because s is smaller than
n, and it's a positive number. But k, k is
just some number in my input. Right? It's
representable in potentially one word.
That's the assumption. But it could have
exponential size, depending on the size of
my word of my machine. I don't know how big
k is relative to n. And so, this is a
pseudopolynomial running time. OK?
It's just a number in my problem, similar
to subset sum, similar to knapsack, which
you guys did in lecture and recitation.
And so, if we ask you on an exam, which we
probably will, whether certain running
times are polynomial or not, that's the
logic that you go about
it. How big is my input?
What is my running time that I'm trying
to evaluate? And can I bound each of those
terms in terms of the size of my input? If
not, then you say it's pseudopolynomial.
OK? All right. So, let's try to tackle
this problem. Already, because we've got
pseudopolynomial, you're thinking
maybe this is going to be knapsack -like or
subset sum -like. OK? What do I
need to? I'm just going to go straight for
subproblems here. Actually,
I should probably say
what my things are. Meh, this is fine. I
gave notation up there, didn't I? OK. So,
we're going to have subproblems. I'm going
to, I want to maximize the number, the
volume of food. So, that should probably
be the output of my subproblem, the max
volume on some subset of dishes.
Right? I'm going to choose suffixes here.
I and some other stuff is going
to be max volume of food possible.
So, I'm going to have
subproblems for plates
pi to pn. I'm going to assume
one indexed here, because why not?
But do I need to remember information along
the way? Yeah. Just like with subset sum
or knapsack, I have this calorie limit.
Right? So, it's going to be really useful
for me to know how many calories I've
already eaten or how many calories I've
already eaten. Or how many calories I have
left in my budget. Right? So, let's say j
using at most j calories from the remaining
dishes. And I need to make sure that I'm
eating exactly some number of sweet plates
in the future. And I need to remember, as I
eat, a sweet plate, the number of sweet
plates I need to eat decreases. And so, I
want to generalize that. I'm going to
put an s prime here to denote eating
exactly
s sweet plates.
OK? So, that's my subproblem.
I've got tons of board space. I'm
going to go ahead and use it. Relation.
We've got xij s prime equals. OK. I'm
trying to maximize volume. Probably, I want
to be maximizing over something. Right?
This combinator is kind of what I like to
call it. Right? Usually, what you're doing
in dynamic programming is making some kind
of choice or combining. Combinating.
Combining. Combining some number of
subproblems and choosing which one's the
best. Right? If you just list a bunch of
options here and don't tell us how to
combine them, that's going to be a problem.
Because we don't know what your dynamic
program is doing at all. So, it's really
useful for you to be able to tell us how
you're combining your subproblems. Here,
we're doing a maximization over the
different volumes possible. If we decide to
eat the plate i, then we get vi in volume.
We fill our tummies with vi in volume. But
then we have to recurse on using one
fewer plate because we can't use that plate
again. And we've decreased the amount
of calories in our budget. And I'm going to
say s prime minus si because si is 1 if
it's sweet and 0 if it's not. So, it's kind
of nice that they kind of gave us this
notation here. I can just subtract it off
if it's there. I don't have to do this
conditional or something. And I don't ever
want to go below these budgets. So,
I'm just going to say if ci is less than or
equal to j and si is less than or equal to
s prime. OK? So, that's going to make sure
that I never have these guys go negative.
Otherwise, I don't eat the plate. And
that's kind of the easy case because I
just go i plus 1, j, s prime. These things
didn't change. I just have one fewer thing
left. So, I'm maximizing over these things.
This one's an always. It's not an if. So, I
just have two choices. I'm maximizing over
them. Topological sort order. Here, I'm
always recursing on a thing with larger i.
Depend on larger i. So,
acyclic. Happy. OK? Base cases.
What's the good case?
I get to the end. I've reached the end of
my menu. I can't look at any more plates.
I've already forbidden myself from going
negative on the calories. So, that should
be all good.
But what do I want on the third parameter?
0. I better have eaten exactly s plates.
So, I want to get down to x, n plus
1 because I'm 1 indexed. j for any j, 0.
That's going to be 0. I get no calories
there. But it's a good thing. It's a good
place. It's fine. 0 is good. All right.
This is done. I don't know. OK. There's
another base case. What's the bad
base case? I get to the end. I'm always
increasing i. And so, I better be doing
something on n plus 1. I got to the end.
j, again, is going to always be. Non
-negative because we're always going to be
in our calorie budget.
But if this is anything other
than s prime greater than 0, if it's
anything but 0, what is that going to be?
Minus infinity. Minus infinity. I never
want to be in this situation. If I do my
dynamic program and I get a minus infinity
up at the top, that means there is no path
to this subprime. So, I'm going to have a
problem here where I'm happy. I'm always
sad. And so, I return that the maximum
volume of food Obert can eat and maintain
his diet is not possible. Essentially,
there aren't s sweet dishes in the thing
whose calorie budget are below my limit.
And that's probably an easier thing to
check than in this bound.
Our original subproblems
now. Solution is given by what?
Just one of our subproblems. It's just
seeing what's the maximum volume. I don't
have to retrace my steps to figure out my
thing. I say one of the subproblems. It's
using all of the things on my menu,
using my entire budget k, and trying to get
exactly s things. That's going to be my
output to my algorithm. And this takes what
time? How many subproblems do I
have? I have n plus 1 subproblems for this
parameter. I have k plus 1 possible things
for this parameter. And I have s plus 1
possible things for this parameter.
So, I get order n k s subproblems.
How much work per subproblem? Just a
max of two things. So, constant work per
subproblem
yields order n k s time total.
OK. So, those are three nice practice
problems for you. Two that are polynomial,
one that's pseudopolynomial. You have one
more example in there, which is the Gokin
-Mon -Poe problem, which is a fun
problem. It involves remembering additional
information that's not really a
pseudopolynomial number in your problem,
but it's the location of where I was last
or where I was going. So, take a look at
that problem. It's another kind of non
-trivial way of expanding subproblems. And
with that, good
luck on your quiz 3.